NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Oversize, 1950-1968 (Box OV 1-OV 12)
  - Legal Case File (Box OV 2)
    - Gray v. Main (elections, Ala.)
      - Background material
        - Voting and population records, Barbour, Bullock, Greene, and Macon counties, 1961-1966
          - Photocopies (Container 214)
            - Box 11 (Box OV 12)
- Index of Legal Cases by Category and State
  Armed Forces
  Civil rights protest demonstrations
  Criminal law
  Domestic relations
  Education
  Elections
  Housing and real property
  Labor
  Miscellaneous
  Public accomodations
  Recreational facilities
  Transportation
- ARMED FORCES
  The Truman administration adopted a policy in 1948 of "equality of treatment and opportunity" in a plan which called for racial integration of the United States armed forces by 1954. The Korean War accelerated the process so that integration was to be implemented by 1952. However, the NAACP continued to receive and investigate complaints of bias relating to assignments, promotion, discipline, or the administration of military justice. Furthermore, integration was much slower in reserve units, and few African Americans received Reserve Officer Training Corps scholarship awards. Finally, the fund challenged lingering segregation in schools, housing, and other collateral activities on military bases.
  - Guam
    - Burns v. Wilson, 1952
  - New York
    - Lawton v. Dewey, undated
  - Pennsylvania
    - Tomlinson v. Selective Serv. Draft Bd., 1948
  - Korean and World War II court martial records, 1943-1952
- CIVIL RIGHTS PROTEST DEMONSTRATIONS
  By 1960, court cases and integration efforts were sometimes accompanied by forms of social protest such as sit-ins and group marches. Demonstrators were often arrested for breach of peace or trespassing and some were defended by the fund.
  - Alabama
    - Alabama v. Allen, 1964-1965
    - Alabama v. Gray, 1964
    - Alabama v. Hanson, 1963
    - Alabama v. Robinson, 1963
    - Banks v. Alabama, 1963-1964
    - Carter v. City of Birmingham, 1965
    - Clemons v. Alabama, 1964
    - Cruikshank v. Alabama, 1964
    - Fowlkes v. Alabama, 1964
    - Johnson v. Alabama, 1964
    - Shelton v. Alabama, 1964
    - Smith v. Alabama, 1963 1964
    - Thomas v. City of Birmingham, 1963
    - Webster v. City of Birmingham, 1963-1965
  - California
    - Hughes v. Lucky Stores, Inc., 1948
  - Louisiana
    - Byrd v. City of New Orleans, 1948
    - Diamond v. Louisiana, 1962-1964
  - Maryland
    - Maryland v. Askin, 1948
  - North Carolina
    - Avent v. North Carolina, 1962
    - North Carolina v. Williams, 1960
  - South Carolina
    - City of Darlington v. Stanley, 1960-1961
- CRIMINAL LAW
  The fund litigated cases in which a defendant claimed denial of due process because of racial discrimination. Usually these cases raised questions about jury selection, coerced confessions, competent legal representation, and unfair sentencing. Some cases involved lynchings; others concerned police misconduct and racial segregation in prisons.
  - Alabama
    - Alabama v. Fikes, 1953
    - Arrington v. Alabama, 1949-1950
    - Fikes v. Alabama, 1953-1956
    - Hamilton v. Alabama, 1964
    - Huff v. Alabama, 1957
    - Middlebrooks v. City of Birmingham, 1964
    - Reeves v. Alabama, 1953-1957
  - California
    - Civil Rights Congress of the City and County of San Francisco v. Warren, 1950
    - Hardyman v. Collins, 1950
    - In re Middlebrooks, undated
    - Nichols v. McGee, 1957
  - Connecticut
    - Connecticut v. Higgs, 1953-1955
    - United States ex rel. Rogers v. Cummings, 1956
  - Florida
    - Florida v. Jordan, 1951
    - Furlow v. Florida, 1965
    - Irvin v. Florida, 1953
    - Shepherd v. Florida, 1950-1952
  - Georgia
    - Georgia v. Henderson, 1950
    - Georgia v. Ingram, 1948
    - Georgia v. Walker, 1966
    - Griffin v. Georgia, 1951
    - Ingram v. Georgia, 1948
    - Jones v. Balkcom, 1953
    - Mosley v. Georgia, 1955
    - Whitus v. Georgia, 1961
    - Worthy v. Foster, 1948
  - Illinois
    - Illinois v. Atkins, 1954
    - Illinois v. DeRose, 1951
    - Williams v. Illinois, 1951
  - Iowa
    - Iowa ex rel. Hooper v. Bennett, 1959-1960
  - Louisiana
    - Guice v. Mayeaux, 1954
    - Leib v. O'Neal, 1954
  - Maryland
    - Adams v. Maryland, 1953
  - Michigan
    - Clark v. Michigan, 1956
  - Mississippi
    - Hawkins v. Mississippi, 1955
    - Johnson v. Mississippi, 1954-1955
    - Kennard v. Mississippi, 1961-1963
    - Mississippi v. Johnson, 1954
    - Robinson v. Mississippi, 1955
    - United States ex rel. Goldsby v. Wiggins, 1957
  - New Jersey
    - Dukes v. Hanna, 1952-1954
    - New Jersey v. Lewis; New Jersey v. Parker, 1948
    - Williams v. Glasco, 1949
  - New York
    - Capel v. Shaw, 1949
    - Cavers v. Grasheim, 1961
    - New York ex rel. Bracey v. Salter, 1949
    - New York v. Cornelius, 1955
    - New York v. Kelly, undated
    - Woodruff v. Village of Port Chester, 1951
  - North Carolina
    - Daniels v. North Carolina, 1949-1950
    - In re Ingram, 1953
    - North Carolina v. Jackson, 1954
    - North Carolina v. Simmons, 1951
  - Ohio
    - Haley v. Ohio, 1948
    - United States v. Brandt, 1954
  - Pennsylvania
    - Brown v. Baldi, 1953-1954
    - Pennsylvania ex rel. Hatton v. Dye, 1953
    - Pennsylvania ex rel. Johnson v. Thomas, 1944
  - Tennessee
    - Barkley v. Tennessee, undated
    - Chandler v. Fretag, 1952
    - Hale v. Tennessee, 1955
    - Kennedy v. Tennessee, 1948
    - Tennessee v. Pillow, 1946
  - Texas
    - Cassell v. Texas, 1949
    - Hill v. Texas, 1942
    - Holland v. Texas, 1948
    - Ivey v. Texas, 1952
    - In re Rooks, 1952
  - South Carolina
    - South Carolina v. Bullock, 1959
    - South Carolina v. Harvey, 1951
  - Utah
    - Neal v. Graham, 1954
  - Virginia
    - Bailey v. Virginia, 1950
    - Barrett v. Jewett, 1950
    - Hampton v. Smith, 1950
    - Leakes v. Virginia, 1953
    - Scull v. Committee on Law Reform & Racial Activities, 1957
    - Tinsley v. City of Richmond, 1961
  - Washington, D.C.
    - Hall v. United States, 1947
- DOMESTIC RELATIONS
  Antimiscegenation laws were challenged, as were those which prohibited interracial cohabitation or which imposed special penalties if the offenders were of different races. Similarly, the fund challenged adoption and child custody cases which were based on racial considerations.
  - New York
    - Meenan v. Meenan, 1954
- EDUCATION
  Discrimination in education was the fund's primary area of litigation from the 1940s to 1960s. Initial efforts were directed at gaining equal facilities and curriculum for students and equal pay for teachers in Negro schools. By the 1950s, it had been clearly demonstrated in the courts that separate schools would never be equal. Thereafter, cases aimed for integration at all levels of public education: first in professional schools, and then in elementary and secondary schools, colleges, and universities.
  - Arizona
    - Phillips v. Phoenix Union High Schools, 1953
  - Arkansas
    - Abernathy v. Izzard, 1955
    - Brewer v. Hoxie School Dist. No. 46 of Lawrence County, 1944, 1955-1956
    - Brown v. Ramsey, 1948-1949
    - Morris v. Williams, 1945
  - California
    - English v. Pasadena School Bd., 1953
    - Romero v. Weakley; Burleigh v. Weakley, 1955
  - Delaware
    - Steiner v. Simmons; Simmons v. Steiner, 1954
    - Wilson v. Beebe; Johnson v. Beebe, 1951
  - Florida
    - Boyd v. Board of Control of Fla., 1949-1951
    - Florida ex rel. Hawkins v. Board of Control, 1950-1958
    - McDaniel v. Board of Pub. Instruction, 1941
    - Sims v. Board of Pub. Instruction, 1950
    - Turner v. Keefe, 1943
  - Georgia
    - Andrews v. Cook, 1955
    - Everett v. Smith, 1949-1950
    - Hunt v. Arnold, 1956
  - Illinois
    - Ayer v. Mann, 1949
    - Davis v. Schultz, 1955
  - Kansas
    - Henry v. Board of Educ., 1955
    - Henry v. Rushton, 1955
  - Kentucky
    - Abbington v. Board of Educ. of Louisville, Ky., undated
    - Dawson v. Farnsley, circa 1950
    - Willis v. Walker, 1955
    - Wilson v. Paducah Junior College, 1949-1953
  - Louisiana
    - Allen v. Louisiana State Bd. of Educ., 1961
    - Angel v. Louisiana State Bd. of Educ., 1956
    - Board of Supervisors of La. State Univ. v. Tureaud, 1955
    - Bright v. Union Parish School Bd., 1954
    - Combre v. John McNeese State College, 1954
    - Constantine v. Southwestern La. Inst., 1954
    - Foister v. Board of Supervisors of La. State Univ. and Agric. and Mechanical College, 1951
    - Freret Civic Improvement Ass'n v. Orleans Parish School Bd., 1952
    - Guillory v. Saint Landry Parish School Bd., 1951
    - Hatfield v. Board of Supervisors, La. State Univ., 1946-1947
    - Heard v. Ouachita Parish School Bd., 1950-1951
    - Howard v. Lincoln Parish School Bd., undated
    - Jamieson v. Louisiana State Bd. of Educ., 1965
    - Johnson v. Board of Supervisors, 1946-1947
    - Lark v. Louisiana Bd. of Educ., 1957
    - LeBeauf v. State Bd. of Educ., 1965
    - McKelpin v. Orleans Parish School Bd., 1941-1942
    - Payne v. Board of Supervisors of La. State Univ., 1951
    - Simmons v. Ouachita Parish School Bd., 1954
    - Tureaud v. Board of Supervisors of La. State Univ., 1953
    - Wells v. Dyson, 1955
    - Westley v. Iberville Parish School Bd., 1953
    - Whitmyer v. Lincoln Parish School Bd., 1954
    - Williams v. Prather, 1955
    - Wilson v. Board of Supervisors of La. State Univ., 1950
  - Maryland
    - Brown v. Board of Educ. of Calvert County, Md., 1937
    - Groves v. Board of Educ., 1956-1958
    - Mills v. Lowndes, undated
    - Mitchell v. Connellee, 1955
    - Tyson v. Byrd, 1949
  - Michigan
    - Henry v. Godsell, 1956
  - Missouri
    - Curators of the Univ. of Mo. v. Bell, 1950
    - Lee v. Board of Educ., 1943
    - Madison v. University of Mo. Medical School, 1950
    - Missouri v. School Dist., 1951
    - Missouri ex rel. Brewton v. Board of Educ., 1949
    - Missouri ex rel. Toliver v. Board of Educ., 1949
  - Mississippi
    - Bates v. Batte, 1947-1951
    - Meredith v. Fair, 1962
  - New Jersey
    - Walker v. Board of Educ.; Anderson v. Board of Educ., 1954
  - New York
    - Bell v. Board of Education, Amityville, N.Y., 1955-1956
    - In re Board of Educ., Union Free School Dist. 9, Town of Hempstead, N. Y., 1949-1950
    - Breslow v. Wilson, 1949-1951
    - Brown v. Union Free School Dist. No. 16, Nassau County, N.Y., 1951
    - In re Hillburn School Dist. 15, 1931-1944
    - In re Jackson, 1955
    - In re Skipwith, Rector, 1958-1959
    - Taylor v. Board of Educ., 1956-1961
    - Tudor v. Board of Educ., 1953
    - In re Ware, 1958-1959
    - Zorach v. Clauson, 1952
  - North Carolina
    - Blue v. Durham Public School Dist., 1949
    - Carson v. Board of Educ. of McDowell Co., N.C., 1955-1957
    - Carson v. Warlick, 1956
    - Covington v. Edwards, 1955-1959
    - Eaton v. Board of Educ. of New Hanover County, N.C., 1953
    - Froneberger v. Huss, 1954
    - McKissick v. Durham City Bd. of Educ., 1958-1959
    - Neville v. Orange County Bd. of Educ., 1961
    - Simmons v. Wallace, undated
    - Stephens v. Board of Graded School Trustees, 1948
    - Stevens v. Hedgpeth, 1947-1948
    - Thomas v. Gray, 1951
    - Vickers v. Chapel Hill City Bd. of Educ., 1960
  - Ohio
    - Clemons v. Board of Educ. of Hillsboro, Ohio, 1954-1956
  - Oklahoma
    - Borrough v. Jenkins, 1955
    - Brown v. Long, 1957
    - Carr v. Cole, 1957
    - Grant v. Taylor, 1954-1955
    - Troullier v. Procter, 1954
  - Pennsylvania
    - Girard Estate, Orphan's Court of Philadelphia, 1955
    - Sealy v. Department of Pub. Instruction, 1957
  - South Carolina
    - Bryan v. Austin, 1956-1957
    - Kennedy v. State Budget & Control Bd., 1955
  - Tennessee
    - Booker v. Tennessee Bd. of Educ. 1955
    - Goss v. Board of Educ. of Knoxville, Tenn., 1958-1961
    - Ex parte Gray, 1951
    - Gray v. Board of Trustees of the Univ. of Tenn., 1951-1952
    - Jackson Colored Teachers' Ass'n v. Callahan, 1944
    - Kelley v. Board of Educ., 1955-1959
    - McSwain v. County Bd. of Educ., 1950-1956
    - Northcross v. Board of Educ., undated
    - Prater v. Tennessee Bd. of Educ., 1958
    - Shannon ex rel. Cox v. Board of Educ., 1954
    - Thomas v. Hibbitts, 1942
    - Ward v. Board of Educ., undated
  - Texas
    - Avery v. Wichita Falls Indep. School Dist., 1956
    - Battle v. Wichita Falls Junior College, 1951-1953
    - Brown v. Board of Trustees, Lagrange Indep. School Dist., 1951
    - Bruce v. Stilwell, 1954
    - Butler v. Matthews, 1950
    - Butler v. Wilemon, 1949
    - Cains v. Green, 1953
    - Christian v. Moore, 1952
    - Delgado v. Bastrop Indep. School Dist., 1948
    - Fleeks v. Stilwell, 1949
    - Hayes v. County School Comm'n, 1959
    - Higgins v. Goodman, 1949
    - Jackson v. McDonald; Lamar State College of Technology v. Jackson, 1956
    - Jennings v. Board of Trustees, 1947
    - Ross v. Rogers, 1957
    - Scruggs v. Loftin, 1952
    - Simmons v. Edwards, 1960
    - Stevenson v. Harris, 1948
    - Thompson v. Portwood, 1952
    - Walker v. Board of Regents of Univ. of Tex., 1954
    - White v. Smith, 1955
    - Whitmore v. Stillwell, 1955
    - Woods v. Stone, 1949
  - Virginia
    - Ashley v. School Bd. of Gloucester County, 1949
    - Blount v. School Bd. of Isle of Wight County, Va., undated
    - Bowler v. School Bd. of the City of Richmond, 1942
    - Brooks v. City School Bd. of Galax, Va., 1959
    - Carter v. School Bd. of Arlington County, Va., 1950
    - Cook v. Board of Educ. of Prince George's City, Va., 1938-1940
    - Corbin v. Board of Educ. of Pulaski County, Va., 1949-1950
    - Freeman v. School Bd. of Chesterfield Co., 1948
    - Goins v. School Bd. of Grayson County, Va., undated
    - Jones v. School Bd., 1960
    - Kelly v. School Bd., 1948
    - Swanson v. University of Va., 1950
    - Virginia v. Billups, 1952
  - Washington, D.C.
    - Gregg v. Sharpe, circa 1950
    - Haley v. Sharpe, 1949
  - West Virginia
    - Anderson v. Board of Educ. of the County of Mercer, W.Va., 1955
    - Dunn v. Board of Educ. of Greenbrier, W.Va., 1955
    - Taylor v. Board of Educ., 1955
- ELECTIONS
  The fund took cases to gain or protect voting rights in general elections and primaries. Other cases concerned electoral district apportionment and strictures on Negro candidates and bloc voting.
  - Alabama
    - Davis v. Schnell, 1949
    - Gray v. Main, 1961-1967
    - Newman v. Searcy, 1949
  - Arkansas
    - Gatlin v. McDaniel, 1950
  - Georgia
    - Franklin v. Harber, 1949
    - Smith v. Baldwin, 1948
  - Louisiana
    - Byrd v. Brice, 1952
    - Scott v. Beard, 1954
    - Ventre v. Ryder, 1959
  - Mississippi
    - Darby v. Daniel, 1957
  - New Mexico
    - Trujillo v. Garley, undated
  - North Carolina
    - Elliott v. Cumberland County Bd. of Elections, 1955
    - Lassiter v. Northampton County Bd. of Elections, 1957
    - Trafton v. Burgges, 1954
  - Oklahoma
    - Hodge v. Tulsa County Election Bd., 1948
  - South Carolina
    - Elmore v. Rice, 1947
  - Texas
    - Perry v. Cyphers, 1951
  - Virginia
    - Kelsey v. Moore, 1946
- HOUSING AND REAL PROPERTY
  The fund challenged racial zoning laws and restrictive covenants which excluded ethnic groups, and segregation or discrimination in federal housing and other public housing aid programs. Other litigation involved individuals who resorted to the courts to protect private property rights, or cases brought against individuals who obstructed integration of residential neighborhoods.
  - Alabama
    - Barnes v. City of Gadsden, Ala., 1953-1959
    - City of Birmingham v. Monk, 1950
    - Morris v. Housing Auth., 1954
    - Tate v. City of Eufaula, undated
    - Watts v. Housing Auth., 1952-1956
  - California
    - Amer v. Superior Court of Calif., 1947
    - Banks v. Housing Auth. of the City and County of San Francisco, 1952-1953
    - Barrows v. Jackson, 1950-1952
    - Burkman v. Liddy, 1942
    - Franklin v. Housing Auth. of the City of Sacramento, 1952
    - Ming v. Horgan, 1954-1957
  - Connecticut
    - Harris v. Clinton, 1955
  - Georgia
    - Cohen v. Public Hous. Admin., 1952-1956
    - Heyward v. Public Hous. Admin., 1954-1956
  - Illinois
    - Clark v. Sandusky, 1951
    - Illinois v. Leighton, 1951
    - Jenkins v. Chicago Hous. Auth., 1953
    - McCormick v. Green, undated
  - Indiana
    - Woodbridge v. Housing Auth., 1952-1953
  - Kentucky
    - Buchanan v. Warley; Harris v. Louisville, 1915-1929
    - Eleby v. Louisville Municipal Hous. Comm'n, 1956-1957
  - Louisiana
    - Stewart v. Clark Terrace Unit One, Inc., 1952-1955
    - Wilson v. Bossier Constr. Co., 1954
  - Maryland
    - Kennard v. McKamer Realty Co., undated
  - Michigan
    - Askew v. Benton Harbor Hous. Comm'n, 1951-1956
    - Flowers v. National Hous. Auth., 1943
    - Hill v. Hamtramck Hous. Comm'n, 1942-1947
    - Lewis v. City of Detroit, 1942-1954
    - Malicke v. Milan, 1948
    - Mrsa v. Reynolds, 1946
    - Phillips v. Naff, 1952
  - Missouri
    - Davis v. Saint Louis Hous. Auth., 1953-1956
    - Venable v. City of Creve Coeur; City of Creve Coeur v. Deilman, 1956
    - Weiss v. Leaon, 1949-1950
  - New Jersey
    - Crawford v. Maher, 1952
    - Miller v. McComb, 1954
    - Seawell v. MacWithey, 1948
    - Taylor v. Leonard, 1954
  - New York
    - Commission against Discrimination v. Pelham Hall Apts., Inc., 1957-1958
    - Dorsey v. Stuyvesant Town Corp., 1947-1948
    - In re Griffin v. City of Schenectady, 1950
    - Hunter v. City of New York, 1952
    - Kemp v. Rubin, 1946
    - Mid-Island Properties v. Johnson, 1953
    - United States v. Mortgage Conference, 1948
  - Ohio
    - Trustees of Monroe Ave. Church v. Perkins, 1947
    - Vann v. Toledo Metro. Hous. Auth., 1953
    - Ward v. Columbus Metro. Hous. Auth., 1954-1955
  - Oregon
    - Foeller v. Housing Auth. of Portland, 1953
    - Namba v. McCourt, 1948
  - Pennsylvania
    - Johnson v. Levitt & Sons, Inc., 1955
    - Pearson v. Olney Gardens, 1955
    - Unger v. Dewalt, 1941
    - Yoshida v. Gelbert Improvement Co., 1946
  - Washington, D.C.
    - Hundley v. Gorewitz, 1942
    - Shanks Village Residents Ass'n v. Cole, 1954
  - Washington, D.C.
    - Taylor v. Blandford, 1945
- LABOR
  Depression era cases often concerned forced labor or peonage. Thereafter, the fund worked to define fair employment practices by challenging discrimination in government employment or by companies receiving government contracts, exclusion of African Americans from professional associations or union membership, especially when unions negotiated contracts and were otherwise consulted on labor practices.
  - Alabama
    - Davis v. Arn, 1950-1953
  - California
    - Bacon v. Local 9, Bricklayers and Tile Setters Union, 1949
  - Connecticut
    - Commission on Civil Rights ex rel. Tilley v. International Bhd. of Elec. Workers Local 35; Commission on Civil Rights ex rel. Stewart v. International Bhd. of Elec. Workers Local 35, 1951
    - International Bhd. of Elec. Workers Local 35 v. Commission on Civil Rights, 1954
  - Illinois
    - Howard v. Local 74, Wood, Wire, & Metal Lathers Int'l Union, 1954
    - Young v. Chicago Hous. Auth., 1952
  - Kansas
    - Betts v. Easley, 1946
  - Kentucky
    - Benjamin v. Louisville & Nashville R.R., circa 1944
  - Maryland
    - Enoch Pratt Free Library v. Kerr, 1945
  - Missouri
    - Howard v. Saint Louis-San Francisco Ry., 1951
  - New York
    - American Jewish Congress v. Arabian American Oil Co., 1959
    - Ivory v. Edwards, 1951
    - Joseph v. Boyce, 1955
    - Ocasio v. Fox, 1952
  - Ohio
    - Turner v. Warner & Swasey Co., 1942
  - Pennsylvania
    - Dargon v. Yellow Cab Co. of Pittsburgh, 1952
  - Rhode Island
    - Hill v. International Bhd. of Boilermakers, 1955
  - South Carolina
    - Derrick v. Local 470, International Union of Operating Eng'rs, 1951-1952
  - Texas
    - Alexander v. Texas, 1954
    - Harvey v. Morgan, 1954
    - Syres v. Oil Workers Union Local 23, 1955
  - Virginia
    - Rolax v. Atlantic Coast Line R.R., 1950
  - Washington, D.C.
    - New Negro Alliance v. Sanitary Grocery Co., 1938
    - Palmer v. Southern Ry., 1948
    - Taylor v. Brotherhood of Ry. & S.S. Clerks, 1951-1952
- MISCELLANEOUS
  Includes cases which do not fit into outlined categories. Of note are the cases involving the NAACP's right to do business in various states in the 1950s, particularly in Texas.
  - California
    - Acheson v. Murakami, 1949 (citizenship of Nisei)
    - Williams v. McClellan, 1953
  - Florida
    - Jackson v. Boger, 1950
  - Georgia
    - Holmes v. City of Atlanta, 1955
  - Illinois
    - Beauharnais v. Illinois, 1952 (free press)
  - Maryland
    - Afro-American Co. v. Owen, 1956-1957 (free press)
    - DeAngelis v. Board of Liquor License Comm'rs for Baltimore, Md., circa 1955 (liquor licensing)
    - Lancaster v. Hammond, 1949 ("Ober Bill Case")
  - Nebraska
    - Batterson v. Omaha Post Number One of the American Legion, 1948 (communists excluded from organization)
  - New Jersey
    - In re Marshall, 1949
  - New York
    - Adler v. Board of Educ. of the City of New York, 1951 (communists barred from teaching, N.Y.)
    - Bailey v. Wilkins, 1950-1951 (NAACP branch dispute)
    - Bright v. NAACP, 1951 (NAACP finances)
    - In re Jacob, 1951
    - New York ex rel. Portnoy v. Strasser, 1951-1952
  - Ohio
    - Burt v. Foust, 1950 (exclusion from American Bowling Congress)
  - South Carolina
    - Earle v. Greenville County and Pickens County, S.C., 1949 (lynching)
  - Texas
    - NAACP v. Texas, 1956-1960
    - Texas v. NAACP, 1956
  - Washington
    - Lesser v. Lesser, 1952
  - Location unknown
    - Dembo v. Siple, 1952 (veterans' cemetery)
- PUBLIC ACCOMMODATIONS
  Segregation in public accommodations, recreational facilities, and transportation were daily manifestations of "Jim Crow." Racial distinctions in public accommodations were usually not imposed by state statutes; many facilities banned African Americans or were segregated by custom, or local ordinance and regulation. Cases of racial discrimination were brought against auditoriums, hospitals and health facilities, hotels, insurance companies, libraries, restaurants, cafeterias, and lunch counters, retail stores, theaters and other places of entertainment.
  - Alabama
    - Alabama v. Johnson, 1963-1965
    - City of Montgomery v. Montgomery Improvement Ass'n, 1956
    - Jones v. Southeastern Greyhound Lines, 1953
  - Arkansas
    - Johnson v. Crawfis, 1954
  - Florida
    - Boldan v. Allen, 1964
    - McDuffie v. Florida Turnpike Auth., 1960-1961
  - Georgia
    - Coke v. City of Atlanta, 1958-1960
  - Hawaii
    - Merrit v. Green Room, 1951
  - Illinois
    - Burroughs v. Sanitary Dist. of Chicago, 1951
    - Stewart v. Lincoln-Douglas Hotel Corp., 1952
  - Iowa
    - Rice v. Sioux City Memorial Cemetery, 1953
  - Kansas
    - Becknell v. Trig, Inc., 1957
    - City of Wichita v. Morton, 1948
  - Kentucky
    - Moorman v. Morgan, 1954
    - Muir v. Louisville Park Theatrical Ass'n, 1953
  - Louisiana
    - Arnaud v. Arnaud's Restaurant, Inc., 1964
  - Maryland
    - Law v. Mayor of Baltimore, 1948
  - Michigan
    - Bishop v. Statler Hotels, 1957
  - New York
    - Castle Hill Beach Club, Inc., v. Arbury, 1955
  - North Carolina
    - Eaton v. Board of Managers of James Walker Memorial Hosp., 1956
    - Hall v. Roanoke-Chowan Hosp., 1965
  - Ohio
    - Colbert v. Coney Island, 1953-1956
    - Fletcher v. Coney Island, Inc., 1954-1956
  - Pennsylvania
    - Manning v. Crowl, 1953
  - Tennessee
    - Mathews v. Orgill, 1958-1960
  - Texas
    - Plummer v. Casey, 1953
    - Williams v. Hilton Hotels Corp., 1958
  - Virginia
    - Boynton v. Virginia, 1959-1960
    - Bradshaw v. Whigam, 1965-1966
    - Henry v. Virginia, 1961-1963
    - Robinson v. Hunter, 1961
  - Washington, D.C.
    - District of Columbia v. John R. Thompson Co., Inc., 1950-1953